A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Administrative Functions, RG 4 FA1798
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Communications, 1943-2017; 2; 9.78 Cubic Feet 28 containers
  - New Releases, 1975-2017; 2.4; 2.85 Cubic Feet 7 letter document boxes and 1 half-letter document box
    - Other, 1982-2008; 2.4.2
      - News Releases, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 41)
        News releases from other organizations which mention Knight Foundation, 2000. Includes Foundation Center.
      - News Releases, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Knight File Number - 3366
        News releases from other organizations which mention Knight Foundation, 2005. Includes release re: appointment of Hodding Carter to a UNC professorship and a KF grant to PBS.
      - Sale of Knight-Ridder to McClatchy Company, 2006 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Knight File Number - 3621
        News release re: sale of Knight-Ridder, Inc. to McClatchy Company for $6.5 billion.
      - Sound Publishing Holdings to buy Beacon Journal, 2006 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 44)
        Knight File Number - 4258
        News release re: sale of the Akron Beacon Journal to Sound Publishing Holdings of Canada.
      - New Report Identifies Characteristics That Drive Foundation Spending Patterns, 2008 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 45)
        Knight File Number - 3774
        News release re: long-terms study of Foundation expenses and compensation conducted by the Foundation Center, GuideStar, and the Urban Institute, all funding partners of KF.
  - Promotional Materials, 1991-2016; 2.5; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    The promotional materials provide background on programs, such as the "College Internship Program," or are informational, like the "How to Apply for a Grant" brochure.
    - How to Apply for a Grant, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 1504
      Brochure with information about the proposal process, includes eligibility requirements, preferences, and frequency of requests.
    - How to Apply for a Grant, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1501
      A brochure sent to people inquiring about grant application. It includes information about the proposal process, (letter of application, the proposal packet), communication practices, eligibility requirements, preferences, and frequency of requests.
    - How to Apply for a Grant, 1993 May-September (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 238
      Brochures sent to people inquiring about grant application. It includes information about the proposal process, (letter of application, the proposal packet), communication practices, eligibility requirements, preferences, and frequency of requests. A revision (9/1996) includes a map showing eligible Knight Foundation cities.
    - How to Apply for a Grant, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1503
      A brochure sent to people inquiring about grant application. It includes information about the proposal process, (letter of application, the proposal packet), communication practices, eligibility requirements, preferences, and frequency of requests. There also is a map showing eligible Knight Foundation cities.
    - College Internship Program Brochures, 1998 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 1117
      Brochures produced for the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation College Internship Program, which began in 1998. Brochure describes the foundation, its purpose in creating the internship program, internship categories and general descriptions of projects.
    - How to Apply for a Grant: Guidelines, 1999 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 2262
      Brochures sent to people inquiring about grant application. It includes information about the proposal process, (letter of application, the proposal packet), communication practices, eligibility requirements, preferences, and frequency of requests. Included is a map showing eligible Knight Foundation cities. 3 copies
    - Grant Guidelines and Application Form, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 2509
      The "Grant Guidelines and Application Form" provides instructions on how to apply for a grant, and contains an application form, with sample responses to application questions.
    - Introduction to Grant Programs, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 2263
      The "Introduction to Grant Programs 2001" brochure explains the changes the Knight Foundation has made to its approach to grant making starting in 2000. More emphasis has been placed on investing in local initiatives in the Knight Foundation's 26 core communities through its Knight Community Partners Program. A section on Frequently Asked Questions is included. 5 copies.
    - Introduction to Grant Programs, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 1972
      The "Introduction to Grant Programs 2002" brochure explains the changes the Knight Foundation has made to its approach to grant making starting in 2000. More emphasis has been placed on investing in local initiatives in the Knight Foundation's 26 core communities through its Knight Community Partners Program. A section on How To Apply for a Grant is included, along with Frequently Asked Questions. 5 copies.
    - The American Journalist in the 21st Century: Key Findings - Informational Packet, 2003 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 2735
      Press release, methodology paper, and key findings for "The American Journalists in the 21st Century", produced by David Weaver, School of Journalism, Indiana University, and sponsored by the Knight Foundation. This 2002 survey continued the series of major national studies of U.S. journalists begun in 1971. The book, based on the survey, is expected to be published summer 2004.
    - Introduction to Grant Programs, c. 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 3371
      The "Introduction to Grant Programs" brochure provides information on how to apply for a grant from KF. Includes a statement of purpose, website links by community, inquiry procedures, and funding priorities. 2 copies.
    - $1,000,000,000: A Billion Reasons to Know Where We're Headed, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 4401
      Postcard announcing that KF had surpassed $1 billion in grants since 1950. Cover features a detail from the portrait of the Knight Brothers. 3 copies.
    - Living Cities, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 4400
      Two versions of an advocacy brochure for Living Cities: "Calling for a New Direction in National Urban Policy" and "What Does It Take To Build Vital Cities?". Both mention KF as an investment partner.
    - Knight International Press Fellowships: Make a Difference, c. 2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 4402
      Recruitment brochure for the Knight International Press Fellowships. (2 copies)
    - Knight News Challenge, Winners Quick Reference, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 5901
      Knight News Challenge, "You invent it. We fund it." A Media Innovation Initiative pamphlet that includes the 2007-2009 winners with name, award, location, and project name and description.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 4511
      Business card, folder and postcard size announcement of the Knight News Challenge, "You invent it. We fund it." Also includes the 2008 winners with name, award, location, and project name and description.
    - Knight Arts Partnership, 2008 February-May (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 4262
      The Knight Arts Partnership is a $40 million commitment by KF to support arts in Miami-Dade and Broward counties. $20 million is for leadership gifts to the New World Symphony, Miami Art Museum and the Museum of Contemporary Aft. $20 million is for challenge grants to individuals or organizations whose ideas will help transform the community through the arts. Included is information on the challenge grants, FAQs, an application, and news releases announcing the new initiative. Also included is a Marketing and Public Relations Report, prepared by The Jeffrey Group, detailing the campaign to reach community arts groups and encourage submissions for arts grants.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2009-2012 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 4543
      News Release; 2009 Project Descriptions and Bios; and Winners Quick Reference document, 2007-2009. Also included are two poster-size graphics illustrating the success of one of the winners: DocumentCloud and the failure of another: Media Bugs.
    - Media Innovation Initiatives, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 4769
      Card briefly explaining 6 KF initiatives: Digital innovation, Community information, National Media Policy, Universal Access, Journalism Education and World Wide Web. (3 copies)
    - Knight Arts Challenge and Knight Arts Program, 2009-2010 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 4726
      Knight Arts Challenge: Card listing 2009 winners and amounts awarded and promotional pieces for the 2010 Challenge includes testimonials of past winners and information in Spanish. Knight Arts Program: Call for arts organizations to register for the "Fall for the Arts Festival" presented by KF on September 12, 2010.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2010 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 4812
      Email from Marc Fest to Staff re: News Challenge Email Forward Day when everyone was asked to help promote the latest News Challenge contest by forwarding a news release re: the Knight News Challenge to their "circle of influence". Also Knight News Challenge Winners Quick Reference, 2007-2010, a booklet with all the winners to date.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2011, 2011 June 22-23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 4946
      Email from Marc Fest to Staff re: News Challenge winners; email from Alberto Ibarguen to staff and trustees re: reaction to the winners. Included is a NY Times web article about the contest, titled, "When Big Data Meets Journalism".
    - Knight Enterprise Fund, c. 2012 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Knight File Number - 5608
      Card, business cards, and stickers promoting the Knight Enterprise Fund.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2013, 2013 January 17-April 5 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Knight File Number - 5148
      KF website story announcing eight mobile ventures win $2.4 million in funding via Knight News Challenge (1/17/2013). Copy of blog posted by John Bracken (with comments) about the 2013 Knight News Challenge, which will focus on Open Government issues (1/30/2013). Also included is a memo from Alberto Ibarguen outlining the new initiative, which strives to be a foundation-wide initiative through the News Challenge but also the Knight Community Information Challenge. Alberto appointed a coordinating committee (chaired by Lilly Weinberg and Damian Thorman) to coordinate both information and collaboration. Also included is a follow-up memo by Lilly about initiative progress.
    - O, Miami Poetry Festival, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Knight File Number - 5198
      Program for the O, Miami Poetry festival, which was funded through the Knight Arts Challenge. O, Miami is a biennial poetry festival with the goal of reaching every person in Miami-Dade County with a poem.
    - Making the Right Choices: A John Cage Centennial Celebration, 2013 February 8-10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Knight File Number - 5209
      Program for a three-day festival celebrating the works of John Cage, which was sponsored by KF at the Knight New Media Center, "Exploring the digital age in classical music." Program includes a quote from Alberto Ibarguen.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2014 March 3-2015 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Knight File Number - 5375
      Announcements of the 2014 challenge theme, "How can we strengthen the Internet for free expression and innovation?", and announcement of winners. This year's challenge represented an unprecedented collaboration between KF, Ford Foundation and Mozilla. The 2015 themes are Elections and Data. The Data challenge was a collaboration between Knight, Data & Society, and Open Society Foundations.
    - Knight Arts Challenge, 2011-2014 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Knight File Number - 4945
      Knight Arts Challenge: advertisement announcing that 2011 winners will be announced on November 29, 2011 and soliciting proposals for next round of funding, in January 2012; advertisement announcing that 2011 winners we be announced on November 28, 2011. Cards announcing the spring 2012 challenge in English, Spanish, and Creole. Card announcing the Knight Arts Challenge Miami 2013 Winners - there were 49 winners, $2.7 million. Card lists the project, a brief description and the award amount (5 copies). Also included are announcements of the 75 finalists for the 2014 South Florida Knight Arts Challenge, 88 for Detroit, and 69 for St. Paul.
    - Knight Cities Challenge, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Knight File Number - 5639
      Announcement of the closing of the 2nd Knight Cities Challenge. 158 finalists were chosen from more than 4,500 submissions. Winners will be announced in the spring.
    - Knight Arts Challenge, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Knight File Number - 5640
      Announcement of the launching of the Knight Arts Challenge Miami. Community Conversations are scheduled in 8 greater Miami locations.
    - Knight News Challenge, 2016 January 26-September 9 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Knight File Number - 5638
      Announcement of the winners for the Knight News Challenge on Data and also announcements of the 2016 challenge theme, "How might libraries serve 21st century information needs?". KF offered webinars, and meetings to encourage submissions. Also included are announcements: 1) the winners of the KNC on Libraries and 2) live stream panel discussions re: Innovation and Society.
  - Publications, 1994-2017; 2.6; 2.51 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes and 1 half-box
    The publications offer insights into specific programs such as the Excellence in Education Program ["Learning to Collaborate" (1996), "Collaborating to Learn" (1999), and "Listening and Learning" (2001)], Art and Culture ["Marketing the Arts" (1999) and "Classical Music Consumer Segmentation Study" (2002)] and the Journalism Program ["Minority Students in Journalism" (1997)].
    - New Audiences Now!: A Report on Lincoln Center Theater's Introductory Membership Program, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 2510
      Bound 38-page booklet made possible by a grant from the Knight Foundation.
    - Community Initiated Development: Coming to the Table with Credibility, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 2511
      Bound 63-page booklet made possible by a grant from the Knight Foundation. It was prepared by the National Main Street Center, a division of the National Trust for Historic Preservation, whose mission is to revitalize traditional downtown and neighborhood commercial areas.
    - Learning to Collaborate: Lessons from School-College Partnerships in the Excellence in Education Pro, 1996 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 239
      Bound 51-page booklet prepared for the Knight Foundation by Policy Studies Associates. Discusses and evaluates the collaboration between schools and colleges in the Excellence in Education program.
    - Minority Students in Journalism: Recruiting, Retaining, Graduating, 1997 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 513
      Bound 32-page booklet prepared for the Knight Foundation by Ralph Lowenstein, dean of the University of Florida College of Journalism and Communications. Discusses and evaluates programs for minorities at Journalism schools..
    - Writing For Learning Journal, Volumes 1 - 3, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
      Knight File Number - 2416
      Three volumes (v. 1 - 1996, v. 2 - 1997, v. 3 - 1998) of the Writing for Learning Journal. Prepared by Northern State University, Aberdeen Public School District: A Collaborative K-16 Writing-Across-the-Curriculum Project funded by the Knight Foundation (2 folders).
    - Collaborating to Learn: More Lessons from School-College Partnerships?, 1999 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 1499
      "Collaborating to Learn: More Lessons from School-College Partnerships? in the Excellence in Education Program," published as a follow-up to the 11/1996 booklet ("Learning to Collaborate"), revisits grantees now that projects have matured. The publication relates new lessons about sustaining collaborations and discusses program achievements. (Prepared by Policies Studies Assoc., Inc.)
    - Marketing the Arts, 1999 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 1500
      "Marketing the Arts: Lessons from a Community in Marketing Collaboration" describes a collaboration of performing arts organizations in Charlotte, NC. KF initiated this program in 1994 to help the North Carolina Blumenthal Performing Arts Center, the Opera Carolina, the Charlotte Repitory Theatre and the North Carolina Dance Theatre.
    - Museum Loan Network News, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 2512
      The newsletter of the Museum Loan Network, the first comprehensive national collection-sharing program, provides a list of grantees and offers news of recent grants. Knight staffer, Gary Burger, appears in a picture taken at the annual meeting of curatorial ambassadors (1999-2000). The MLN is funded by the Knight Foundation and the Pew Charitable Trusts. 3 copies of 1999/2000 issue.
    - Immunization Initiative: Executive Summary, 2001 March (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 2513
      In 1994, the Knight Foundation launched a $1.7 million, two-year grant program to improve immunization rates for infants and toddlers in Knight Foundation communities nationwide. In 1996, additional two-year follow-up grants were also awarded. This report summarizes the structure and design, activities, outcomes and lessons learned from the initiative. A list of grantee organizations is enclosed. Soft-bound, ten pages, 3 copies.
    - Listening and Learning: Community Indicator Profiles of Knight Foundation Communities and the Nation, c. 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
      Knight File Number - 2387
      Soft cover book. Listening and Learning: Community Indicator Profiles of Knight Foundation Communities and the Nation, a report prepared by the Knight Foundation and other partners. The report represents a Knight Foundation effort to embark on a social indicators project designed to give visibility to factors effecting civic health in the 26 Knight communities. [3 copies]
    - Building Capacity in Nonprofit Organizations edited by Carol De Vita and Cory Fleming, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4094
      Soft cover book. The research, seminar and report were supported by the Knight Foundation. The report aims to advance the ongoing conversation about capacity building, intending to push toward the intersection where research informs practice. Penny McPhee provided the introduction to the volume.
    - Museum as Catalyst for Interdisciplinary Collaboration: Beginning a Conversation, 2002 January (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 2514
      The Museum Loan Network funded by the Knight Foundation and the Pew Charitable Trusts, was the first comprehensive national collection-sharing program. This booket consists of proceedings of a series of convenings hosted by MLN in 2000-2001. The meetings gathered innovative leaders from different disciplines to explore a number of interrelated issues, challenges and opportunities affecting collaboration and today's museums.
    - Child Trends Research Briefs, 2002 May-September (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 2515
      Issue 1: "Preventing Teenage Pregnancy, Childbearing and Sexually Transmitted Diseases: What the Research Shows", May 2002 (3 copies) Issue 2: "Encouraging Teens to Adopt a Safe, Healthy Lifestyle: A Foundation for Improving Future Adult Behaviors", June 2002 (3 copies) Issue 3: "Helping Teens Develop Healthy Social Skills and Relationships: What the Research Shows about Navigating Adolescence", July 2002 (3 copies) Issue 4: "Educating America's Youth: What Makes a Difference", August 2002 (3 copies) Issue 5: "Promoting Positive Mental and Emotional Health in Teens: Some Lessons from Research", September 2002 ( 3 copies) Research Briefs is based on a comprehensive review of adolescent development research. The American Teens series provides a special look at "What Works" in youth development in partnership with the Knight Foundation.
    - Harmony: Forum of the Symphony Orchestra Institute, 2002 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 2516
      Harmony, biannual publication of the Symphony Orchestra Institute. Issue No. 15 includes an article on "The Wolf Report and Baumol's Curse" Dr. Tom Wolf is a consultant with the Magic of Music initiative. Also included is an article by Penelope McPhee, "Orchestra and Community: Bridging the Gap", based on her remarks at a Magic of Music retreat. (3 copies)
    - Final Report: Classical Music Consumer Segmentation Study, 2002 October-2003 April (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 2396
      Soft cover book. Classical Music Consumer Segmentation Study: How Americans Relate to Classical Music and Their Local Orchestras. Prepared by Audience Insights and commissioned by the Knight Foundation and other partners as part of the second phase of the Magic of Music initiative. The report "offers a sweeping view of an art form in transition and an orchestra field increasingly detached from its potential customers." Included is a cd-rom of a Minnesota Public Radio recording of an interview with Alan Brown, Audience Insight [3 copies]. The third copy is from the second printing, April 2003, which includes corrected copy.
    - While You Were Sleeping, 2006 April (Box 2)
      Knight File Number - 4095
      While You Were Sleeping brochure explains how people can "join in on the new work the Knight Foundation is doing and, through the Knight Brothers 21st Century Challenge, invite you to join in on the new work you plan to do." Forward by Alberto Ibarguen Includes information on the Knight New Media Center, the Knight-Batten Awards for Innovation in Journalism, and Sunshine Week. (3 copies)
    - Newsroom Training: Where's the Investment?, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 2518
      "Newsroom Training: Where's the Investment?": A study for the Council of Presidents of National Journalism Organizations. Includes the findings of a survey conducted by Princeton Survey Research Associates for the Council of President of National Journalism Organizations and funded by the Knight Foundation. Introduction is by Eric Newton. (3 copies)
    - Issues Brief - Magic of Music, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 2397
      Issues Brief: A continuing discussion of issues, practices and changes in symphony orchestra organizations. No. 1: Orchestra & Community: Bridging the Gap, February 2003 No. 2: Bridging the Gap: Orchestra & Classical Music Listeners, June 2003 No. 3: Bridging the Gap: Innovations to Save Our Orchestras, October 2003 No. 4: Initiators & Responders: A New Way to View Orchestra Audiences, July 2004 No. 5: Smart Concerts: Orchestras in the Age of Edutainment, December 2004 The pamphlets were designed to continue the discussion begun a decade ago with partners in the symphony orchestra field in Knight Foundation's Magic of Music initiative. (3 copies each)
    - Listening and Learning: Community Indicator Profiles of Knight Foundation Communities and the Nation, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
      Knight File Number - 2694